Finding Aid for Elly Peterson papers 1943-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elly Peterson papers 1943-2006 1961-1980
Peterson, Elly, 1914-
Michigan Republican Party official, 1961-1969, assistant chairman of the national Republican Party, 1963-1964 and 1969-1970, candidate for, U.S. senate in 1964, and co-chair of ERAmerica, a national organization promoting the ratification of the Equal Rights Amendment. Papers consist of correspondence, reports, speeches, organizational records of ERAmerica, scrapbooks and photographs.
852153 Aa 2UAm
25 linear feet
4 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers of Elly M. Peterson (Donor No. 4155 ) were acquired by the Bentley Library in various accessions beginning in 1964. Periodic additions have been received.
The collection is open for research.
Elly McMillan Peterson was born in New Berlin, Illinois on June 5, 1914. She was educated at William Woods College in Fulton, Missouri and Northwestern University in Chicago, and was a graduate of Suburban Business College in Oak Park, Illinois. In 1935, she married William M. Peterson. Except for a twenty-two month stint overseas with the American Red Cross during World War II, Peterson worked in a variety of secretarial and office management positions in the Chicago and Kalamazoo, Michigan area from 1933 to 1957. She moved to Michigan sometime around 1950 eventually making Charlotte, Michigan her permanent residence.
Early on in her life, Peterson began taking an interest in Republican party politics. At age 21, she became a member of the Oak Park Young Republicans. Following her move to Michigan, she worked for the Republican State Central Committee in a number of different capacities, doing secretarial work and performing various campaign assignments. For some of this period of time, roughly 1957 to 1961, Peterson served as aide to state party chairman, Lawrence B. Lindemer. In 1961, the level of her responsibilities increased when she was appointed Republican field service representative and later Republican state vice chairman. She was re-elected to this two-year position again in 1963. In 1965, she was elected Republican state chairman, the first woman from a major political party to receive that honor. She served until 1969 when she went to work for the national Republican party.
Elly Peterson's rise within the state party had not gone unnoticed by national Republican figures. She was closely associated with the successful campaigns of Governor George Romney, where her organizational skills, especially in enlisting the support of women voters, had propelled the Michigan governor into the national spotlight as a strong presidential possibility. She was selected assistant chairman of the Republican National Committee from 1963 until July 1964 (when she resigned to run unsuccessfully against Philip Hart for his United States Senate seat). She was re-appointed assistant chairman in 1969 serving until December 1970 when she temporarily retired from partisan politics. As assistant chairman, Peterson was responsible for the Action Now program that was established to involve special voter groups in party politics.
During the next several years in the 1970s, Peterson was involved in a number of different women's organizations. Beginning in 1972, Peterson was a member of Delegation for Friendship Among Women and made trips to China and to many of the countries of the Middle East. The purpose of each visit was to promote international friendship among women. In 1974, she served as organizational director of the National Center for Voluntary Action; and in 1975, she contributed her talents to the American Women for International Understanding and the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year. Among all of the issues of this period, Peterson was undoubtedly most devoted to passage of the Equal Rights Amendment. In 1976, she was made co-chair (along with Liz Carpenter) of ERAmerica, an organization established to "provide a national focus for the ERA ratification campaign and to channel money and resources into the unratified states." At that time, ratification of the amendment was stalled, and one of the purposes of ERAmerica was to pump money and enthusiasm into the ratification process. During her two years as co-chair, Peterson was a tireless speaker and effective advocate of the ERA. In 1978, Peterson resigned as co-chair but continued her advocacy in any way she thought useful.
In 1976, Peterson interrupted her retirement from Republican party politics when she accepted on an interim basis the position of deputy chairman of the President Ford Committee. In this organization set-up to run Gerald Ford's election campaign, Peterson was responsible for organizing special voter groups and group volunteers in the presidential campaign. Peterson resigned as deputy chairman after the nominating convention but continued on with People for Ford, an organization that drew together special interest voting blocs.
At the conclusion of the campaign, Peterson continued working for ERAmerica, and then with the failure of the amendment's passage, she devoted herself to civic and charitable organizational work.
The Elly McMillan Peterson papers document the career of a Republican Party activist and official, advocate of the Equal Rights Amendment, and candidate for the U.S. Senate. The papers, comprised largely of correspondence, reports and memoranda, are organized into seven series: Republican Party Activities, ERAmerican, Other Organizational Activities, Personal/Biographical, Speeches, Photographs, Scrapbooks/Clippings.
Subjects:
China--History--1949-; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; International Women's Year, 1975.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Politicians--Michigan.; Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Presidents--United States--Election--1976.; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Congress--Elections, 1964.; United States--Congress--Elections--1966.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1970.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Women's rights--United States.; ERAmerica (Organization); American Women for International Understanding.; National Women's Conference (1st: 1977: Houston, Tex.); Women in politics--Michigan.; Scrapbooks.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Children.; Costumes.; Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Graduation ceremonies.; Interiors.; Laborers.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Peterson, Elly Maude, 1914-2008; Political elections--1964.; Politics and government.; Railroad passenger cars.; Republican Party (Mich.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Rewards and prizes.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Romney, Lenore LaFount.; Women.; Women--Political life.; Women--Work.; Women's rights.
Contributors:
Bliss, Ray Charles, 1907-1981.; Bolger, Ray.; Brooke, Edward W. (Edward William), 1919-2015; Chafee, John H., 1922-1999; Dirksen, Everett McKinley.; Evans, Daniel J., 1925-; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Morton, Thruston B. (Thruston Ballard), 1907-1982.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Percy, Charles H., 1919-2011; Riegle, Donald W., 1938-; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Romney, Lenore LaFount.; Stassen, Harold E. (Harold Edward), 1907-2001; Wilson, Robert Carlton, 1909-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Republican Party Activities
  The first series, and by far the largest set of files, has been labelled Republican Party Activities (17 linear ft.; 1958-1985). Grouped by period of time, this series really covers Peterson's entire career as she was a lifelong Republican. As she held many different position within the party, the series naturally breaks down into chronological divisions: 1958-1964, 1965-1970, 1971-1979, and 1980-1985. Each of these chronological divisions begins with a set of files (arranged roughly by chronology) that include correspondence, memoranda, and other forms of communication. These files are then followed by sub-series of material either resulting from specific activities within the party or offices held either within the state or national Republican party. Thus files pertaining to Peterson's campaign for the U.S. Senate in 1964 will be found within the 1958-1964 division and files created while serving with the President Ford Committee in 1976 will be found in the 1971-1979 division. Other Republican party material will of course be found within genre series - Speeches, Photographs, and Scrapbooks/Clippings.
  - 1958, 1961-1964
    - Chronological files
      (correspondence, memoranda, etc.)
      - Undated; 1958, 1961-March 1963 (Box 1)
      - April-December 1963 (Box 2)
      - Undated 1964 (Box 2)
      - January-April 20, 1964 (Box 3)
      - April 21-August 6, 1964 (Box 4)
      - August 7-October 1964 (Box 5)
      - November-December 1964 (Box 6)
    - Peterson Senatorial Campaign Miscellanea 1964
      - Campaign biography (Box 6)
      - Campaign brochures, etc., 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Speeches of EMP, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Schedules January-November 1964, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - 1965-1970
    - Chronological files
      - January-August 1965 (Box 6)
      - September 1965-March 1967 (Box 7)
      - April 1967-1968 (Box 8)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 9)
    - Distributed papers
      (reports, newsletters, schedules, background information)
      - 1965-1970, undated (Box 9)
    - Republican National Committee Assistant Chair files 1969-1970
      - State files 1969-1970
        (arranged alphabetically by name of state)
        - Alabama-California (Box 9)
        - Colorado-Michigan (Box 10)
        - Michigan-New Hampshire (Box 11)
        - New Jersey-Wyoming (Box 12)
          (also includes foreign and U.S. possessions)
      - Inter-office correspondence
        - 1969 (Box 12)
        - 1970 (Box 13)
      - Juanita Hunter (Assistant to EMP) Files
        - Copies of EMP correspondence June 1969-September 1970, 23 folders (Box 13)
      - Mass mailings 1969-1970 (Box 13)
        (to National Committeewomen, Republican women leaders, etc.)
      - Political campaign files
        - 1969
          - Montana (George Mather) (Box 13)
          - New Jersey (William Cahill) (Box 13)
          - Virginia (Linwood Holton) (Box 13)
        - 1970
          - Michigan (Lenore Romney)
            - Michigan visits by EMP (Box 13)
            - EMP memos and reports (Box 13)
            - General correspondence (Box 13)
            - Staff lists (Box 13)
            - Strategy (Box 13)
            - Anti-Hart material (Box 13)
            - Press and advertisements (Box 13)
            - Minority involvement (Box 13)
            - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
      - Press releases (regarding EMP) (Box 14)
      - Publication: Monday (Box 14)
        (often with articles by or about EMP while with RNC)
      - Republican Women's Federation, 1965-67 (Box 14)
      - Schedules 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Speech file
        - Text of speeches, 3 folders (Box 14)
        - Listing of speaking engagements 1969-1970 (Box 14)
        - Engagement files 1969-1970, 17 folders (Box 14)
      - Topical files (mainly RNC activities) 1967-1970
        - Flying Squadron-X Group 1967-1968 (Box 14)
          (Republican women's group)
        - Negro Women's Advisory Council (Box 14)
        - Republican National Committee organizational notebook circa 1969 (Box 14)
        - Republican Foundation (Box 14)
        - Retirement miscellanea (Box 14)
          (includes sample of letters received upon announcement)
        - Voluntary Action (Box 14)
        - Women and the Nixon Administration (Box 14)
        - Women in Politics (collation of questionnaire) (Box 14)
        - Women (miscellaneous) (Box 14)
  - 1971-1979
    - Chronological files (Box 15)
      - 1971-1979, 18 folders (Box 15)
    - Topical file 1976
      (mainly President Ford Committee)
      - American Political Report (Box 15)
      - Bipartisan Conference of State Party Chairmen (Box 15)
      - Blacks, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Business and Professional Groups for Ford (Box 15)
      - Caravans (Box 15)
      - Carter, Jimmy (Box 15)
      - Catholics for Ford (Box 15)
      - Celebrities for Ford (Box 15)
      - Citizens for Ford (Box 15)
      - Connally, John (Box 15)
      - Convention (Republican National Convention)
        - General (Box 15)
        - Caucus Teams (Box 15)
        - Committee (Box 15)
        - Organization (Box 15)
        - Presidential nomination and acceptance (Box 15)
        - Schedule and events (Box 15)
        - Schedule (EMP) (Box 15)
        - Vice President (Box 15)
        - Women (Box 15)
        - Young Republicans (Box 15)
      - Debates (Box 15)
      - Doctors for Ford (Box 15)
      - Ethnics (Box 15)
      - Farmers for Ford (Box 16)
      - Finance (Box 16)
      - First Family (Box 16)
      - Handicapped (Box 16)
      - Invitations (accepts) (Box 16)
      - Issues (Box 16)
      - Jews for Ford (Box 16)
      - Keyes, Robert (Box 16)
      - Labor Day (Box 16)
      - Lindemer, Lawrence (Box 16)
      - Memos, 6 folders (Box 16)
      - Michigan Republican State Committee (Box 16)
      - National Advisory Board (Box 16)
      - Older Americans (Box 16)
      - Overseas Voters (Box 16)
      - People for Ford
        - General (Box 16)
        - Press releases (Box 16)
        - Regional reports (Box 16)
        - Special groups (Box 16)
        - Staff reports (Box 16)
      - Peterson, Elly (personal) (Box 16)
      - Phone banks (Box 16)
      - Polls (Box 16)
      - President Ford Committee
        - General (Box 16)
        - Fact book (Box 16)
        - Newsletters (Box 16)
        - Press releases (Box 16)
        - State organizations (Box 16)
        - Steering Committee (Box 16)
      - Presidential messages (Box 16)
      - Republican National Committee (Box 16)
      - Republican Women's Task Force (Box 16)
      - Schedule (Box 16)
      - Scheduling-First Family (Box 16)
      - Special events (Box 16)
      - Wednesday Coffee Group (Box 16)
      - Women (miscellaneous) (Box 16)
      - Women for President Ford
        - General (Box 16)
        - Congressional letter (Box 16)
        - Kickoff (June 13) (Box 16)
        - Memoranda (Box 16)
        - National Advisory Board (Box 16)
        - Newsletter (Box 16)
        - Recruitment (Box 16)
        - Regional directors (Box 16)
      - Youth (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - State files 1976 (Box 17)
      (correspondence with Ford supporters)
      - Alabama to Wyoming, 59 folders (Box 17)
    - Correspondence 1972-1979, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - 1980-
    - Correspondence 1980-1985, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - George Bush for President materials 1980 (Box 17)
    - Michigan gubernatorial campaign 1982, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Nomination of Martha Seger to Federal Reserve Board 1984 (Box 17)
- ERAmerica 1971-1982
  The series ERAmerica relates to Peterson's work within this organization to obtain passage of the Equal Rights Amendment. The series (1.5 lin. ft.; 1971-1982) includes material that predates the establishment of ERAmerica but which relates to women's issues in general. The files have been arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Coalition Update
    - 1976-1979 (Box 18)
    - 1980-1992, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Corporate Board Meetings
    - 1976 (Box 18)
    - 1977 (Box 18)
    - 1978 (Box 18)
    - 1979 (Box 18)
    - 1980 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence
    - undated (Box 18)
    - January-June 1976 (Box 18)
    - July-December 1976 (Box 18)
    - 1977 (Box 18)
    - 1978 (Box 18)
    - 1979 (Box 18)
    - 1980- (Box 18)
  - Economic Sanction Program (Box 18)
  - Equal Rights Amendment Miscellaneous 1968-1980 (Box 18)
  - Equal Rights Amendment Arguments/Position Papers/Interpretations, undated 1971-1973 (Box 18)
  - ERAmerica Report 1980-1981 (Box 18)
  - Financial Report, Fundraising, etc
    - 1976 (Box 18)
    - 1977 (Box 18)
    - 1978 (Box 18)
  - Mail Day October 23, 1978 (Box 18)
  - Mailings 1976-1981 (Box 18)
  - Mailings to Board, Steering Committee, etc
    - undated (Box 18)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 18)
    - 1978 (Box 18)
    - 1979 (Box 18)
    - 1980-82 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous 1976-1979 (Box 18)
  - Mormon Church and ERA 1979 (Box 18)
  - News Releases 1976-1980 (Box 18)
  - News Releases (Other Organizations) 1977-1979 (Box 18)
  - Organizational Material 1976-1980 (Box 19)
  - Organizational Support and Opposition, undated, 1978-79 (Box 19)
  - Programs for Peterson Appearances 1976-1980 (Box 19)
  - Radio Campaigns [includes two audio-cassettes] 1981 (Box 19)
  - Reagan (Ronald) Position on ERA 1976 (Box 19)
  - Rescission, 1977-79 (Box 19)
  - Resolutions undated (Box 19)
  - Romney, George, Position on ERA, undated 1980 (Box 19)
  - Resource Materials/Published Material 1979 (Box 19)
  - Speeches, undated, 1971-1978 (Box 19)
  - Statements (by others), 1971-1979 (Box 19)
  - State Activities
    - Arkansas undated (Box 19)
    - Colorado 1976 (Box 19)
    - Florida 1978 (Box 19)
    - Illinois
      - General 1976 (Box 19)
      - Springfield June 6, 1982 (Box 19)
    - Indiana, 1975-76 (Box 19)
    - Michigan, 1980-81 (Box 19)
    - Missouri 1978 (Box 19)
    - North Carolina 1978 (Box 19)
    - Oklahoma 1978 (Box 19)
    - South Carolina 1980 (Box 19)
    - Various States, 1980-82 (Box 19)
  - State Reports, undated 1978 (Box 19)
  - Trips undated (Box 19)
- Other Organizational Activities
  Papers from Peterson's other group activities have been put into Other Organizational Activities (1 lin. ft.; 1969-1983). These files document in part Peterson's many trips abroad with women's organizations, notably to China and the Middle East.
  - American Women for International Understanding
    - Correspondence 1977-1978 (Box 19)
    - Soviet Union, et al. 1969 (Box 19)
    - Visit of China Women's Federation to United States 1979 (Box 19)
  - Delegation for Friendship Among Women
    - China trip Proposal 1973 (Box 19)
    - Mideast Trip 1974 (Box 19)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 19)
  - Women for International Understanding
    - China Trip
      - 1975, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - "An Elly's Eye View of China," 1975 (Box 19)
  - International Women's Year
    - Commission
      - Conference 1975-1976 (Box 20)
      - Correspondence 1975-1976 (Box 20)
      - ERA Committee Meeting 1975 (Box 20)
      - Miscellaneous 1975-1976 (Box 20)
    - National Women's Conference
      - Houston Women's Conference 1977-1978 (Box 20)
      - Memoranda and Correspondence 1977-1978 (Box 20)
      - "Report from Houston and NWC 1977," 1977 (Box 20)
  - National Center for Voluntary Action 1975 (Box 20)
  - National Women's Political Caucus 1971 (Box 20)
  - Republican Action Center Program, Ripon meeting 1973 (Box 20)
- Personal/biographical 1955-2006
  Personal/Biographical (0.5 lin. ft.; 1955-2006) includes information about awards received by Peterson and some of her private writings.
  - Awards 1964-1985 (Box 20)
  - Biographical information (Box 20)
  - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Column: "To the Ladies" from National Bowlers Journal and Billiard Revue, 1946-1947 (Box 20)
  - Desk calendars (Box 20)
  - Guestbook from reception upon occasion of her retirement as assistant chairman of the Republican National Committee December 1970 (Box 20)
  - Honorary Doctorate 1970 (Box 20)
  - Later correspondence and memorabilia 1989-2006, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Letters from public figures 1962-2000, 6 folders (Box 20)
    (includes some photocopies; originals of these items have been placed in the vault)
  - Miscellaneous 1962-1979, undated (Box 20)
  - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame
    - 1983 (Box 20)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 20)
  - Telegrams of congratulations following her speech at Republican National Convention 1964 (Box 20)
  - A Tribute to Elly Peterson 1984 (Box 20)
  - A Tribute to Elly Peterson 1984: Volume entitled: "A celebration of Elly Peterson June 9, 1984" (Volume 1)
  - Travels
    - circa 1955 (Box 20)
    - 1963 (Box 20)
    - New Zealand 1981 (Box 20)
  - Writings/Observations 1972-1988 (Box 20)
- Speeches 1953-1996
  Speeches (1 lin. ft.; 1953-1996) includes both manuscripts of her speeches and also published copies. Other speeches of Peterson will be found (as indicated) in the Republican Party Activities and ERAmerica series.
  - Speech Index undated (Box 25)
  - 1953 (Box 25)
  - 1964 (Box 25)
  - National Republican Committee
    - 1964, 3 folders (Box 25)
    - 1965 (Box 25)
    - 1966, 3 folders (Box 25)
    - 1967 (Box 25)
    - 1968, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - 1969 (Box 25)
  - circa 1970s (Box 25)
  - 1970-1977 (Box 25)
  - 1978 (Box 25)
  - 1979 (Box 25)
  - 1980 (Box 25)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 25)
  - Women's Issues undated (Box 25)
- Audio-Visual Materials circa 1950-2003
  The Audio-Visual materials series consists of photographs, sound recordings, videotapes and a dvd. The photographs include some portraits and personal snapshots, but the bulk of the images relate to Republican Party functions, political campaigns and her other political activities. The series includes images of many prominent Republican, including Richard Nixon, Gerald Ford, Ronald Reagan and George Romney. The sound recordings and videotapes include several interviews with Peterson, campaign messages and a tribute to Peterson.
  - Photographs
    - Biographical/Personal
      - General [snapshots, portraits] (Box 21)
      - Honorary Doctorate, Woods College 1970 (Box 21)
      - Honorary Law Degree, Eastern Michigan University 1976 (Box 21)
      - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame Awards Dinner 1985 (Box 21)
      - Travels in the Orient 1955 1963 (Box 21)
    - Republican Party--Michigan
      - General (Box 21)
        (campaigns, dinners; include Richard Nixon, George Romney, John Tower et al.)
      - Senate Campaign 1964 (Box 21)
    - Republican Party--National Committee
      - General [dinners, awards, Nixon snapshot] (Box 21)
      - Inauguration--Nixon 1969 (Box 21)
      - 11th Annual Republican Women's Conference 1963 (Box 21)
      - "An Evening With Elly," 1969 (photo album) (Box 21)
      - Retirement as Assistant Chairman RNC 1970 (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
    - Later accessions
      - ERA activities (Box 21)
      - Family and friends (Box 21)
      - Ford, Gerald and family (Box 21)
        (see also oversize folder UAm)
      - Groups (Box 21)
      - Michigan subjects (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
      - Nixon/White House (Box 21)
      - Political activities (Box 21)
      - Portraits (Box 21)
      - Romney family (Box 21)
      - Snapshots (Box 21)
      - Women's activities (Box 21)
  - Photograph Albums
    - Retirement from Republican National Committee December 31, 1970 (Box 21)
    - Elly Peterson Day June 30, 1985 (Box 21)
  - Videotapes
    - A Tribute to Elly Peterson June 9, 1984, Beta videotape (Box 21)
    - Interview with EP by William S. Ballenger May 1, 1995, 55 minutes VHS videotape (Box 21)
    - Interview with EP, Des Plaines, Illinois August 15, 2003, VHS videotape (Box 21)
  - DVD (Box 21)
    - "Elly Peterson: A Woman You Should Know" (Courthouse Square Association)
  - Sound Recordings
    - "An Evening with Elly Peterson" 1969, Audio-cassette (Box 21)
    - Elly Peterson for U.S. Senate 1964, Phonorecord, 2 60-second cuts (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks/Clippings 1943-circa 1980